Guide to the Giuliano Garavini Collection AD.MC.038
New York University Abu Dhabi Library
Giuliano Garavini collection
1960 - 1997
New York University Abu Dhabi Library
Garavini, Giuliano, 1976-
AD.MC.038
404.6 Megabytes in 113records (PDF)
Digital copies, in PDF format, of minutes of conference meetings of the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC), and associated documents, from the beginning of the conference in 1960 up to 1986, acquired by historian Giuliano Garavini during the research and writing of his book "The Rise and Fall of OPEC in the Twentieth Century."
Conditions governing access
Materials can only be accessed by permission of the donor, and must be viewed onsite at New York University Abu Dhabi. Please contact Archives and Special Collections at the New York University Abu Dhabi Library (nyuad-asc-group@nyu.edu) for further information.
Immediate source of acquisition
Gift of Giuliano Garavini, 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged largely in chronological order, with minutes of meetings and related documents having been placed in one of five series by date: 1960-1969, 1970-1975, 1976-1980, 1981-1985, and 1986. An additional folder contains copies of two published compilations of press releases and statements issued by OPEC between 1960 and 1997.
Biographical note
Giuliano Garavini (born 1976) is an Italian historian and member of the Faculty of Humanities at the Universita degli Studi, Roma Tre, in Rome, as well as a former Senior Research Fellow in the Humanities at NYU Abu Dhabi. He earned a doctorate in international history from the University of Florence in 2006.
He has mainly written about European integration, decolonization and the Global South, the history of energy and petroleum. He has taught and received fellowships in various institutions including the European University Institute (EUI), the Graduate Institute in Geneva, RomaTre University, the University of Bologna and the University of Padua.
He is the author among others of "After Empires. European Integration, Decolonization and the Challenge from the Global South, 1957-1986" (2012), and has recently co-edited "Oil Shock. The 1973 Crisis and its Economic Legacy" (2016), "Counter-Shock. The Oil Counter-Revolution of the 1980s" (2018), and "The Rise and Fall of OPEC in the Twentieth Century" (Oxford University Press, 2019).
Content Description
The Guiliano Garavini collection consists of digital copies of meeting minutes of OPEC Conference meetings, with other selected attached documents, beginning with the first conference in 1960, and extending through the 80th meeting of the Conference, in December 1986. Includes copies of OPEC resolutions and press releases dating from 1960 to 1997. Digital copies exist as PDF files. Files were obtained by Garavini during the research and writing of his book, "The Rise and Fall of OPEC in the Twentieth Century."
The minutes of the meetings, arranged chronologically by meeting date, show the evolution of the organization and development of its policies, as it dealt with questions of how best to maximize the position of its member states as oil producers in the developing world in response to consumer demand from industralized nations. From the earliest meetings, topics represented included attempts to coordinate pricing of crude oil, how to address the question of price differentials by type of crude and region where it was produced, the nationalization of oil companies in some member states, the role of national oil companies in member states in response to outside oil companies, and whether to set production ceilings applicable to all member states, in order to strengthen the position of member states and to stabilize prices to their benefit, among other recurring issues.
The challenges faced by the cartel are documented these minutes through events and trends that members responded to, such as competition from increasing production by non-member nations (such as that from the development of North Sea oil fields by Norway and the United Kingdom in the 1970s), the oil embargo in response to the Arab-Israeli war of 1973, the devaluation of the U.S. dollar (the currency in which crude oil was priced and traded), fluctuating consumer demand, inflation, and other economic trends.
Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries.; Petroleum industry and trade.; Energy policy.
- Minutes of OPEC meetings, 1960-1969; 75.0 Megabytes in 18 PDF documents.
  - 1st meeting [no minutes available], 1960 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_001)
    General
    No minutes of meeting available.
  - 2nd meeting: Draft minutes of the Second Meeting of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, Caracas, January 15-21, 1961 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_002)
    Topics covered:
    Delegations present: Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Discussion of administrative structure of OPEC, its budget, and the proposed location of its headquarters, and nomination of Juan Pablo Perez Alfonzo to chairmanship. Also included discussion of requirements for admission to membership, including acceptance of Qatar as member and review of requests from Trinidad and Colombia. Text of speeches delivered by Fouad Rouhani (Iran), Juan Pablo Perez Alfonzo (Venezuela), Mohamed Salman (Iraq), and the President of Venezuela, Romulo Betancourt.
    Physical characteristics
    PDF, 58 pages, 3 MB.
  - 3rd meeting [no minutes available] (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_003)
  - 4th meeting [no minutes available] (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_004)
  - 5th meeting: Proceedings of the Second Session of the Fifth Conference, Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, December 25-31, 1963 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_005)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela Topics covered included determining budget for 1964, appointment of auditors, reorganizstion of the Secretariat, discussion of country to host headquarters (Switzerland), proposed membership of Emirate of Abu Dhabi, appointment of Abdul Rahman Bazzaz (Iraq) to succeed Fouad Rouhani as Secretary General, the status of negotations between OPEC and various oil companies, and mechanisms for determining the price of crude oil. Text of speeches by Crown Prince Faisal of Saudi Arabia, Ahmad Zaki Yamani (Saudi Arabia).
    PDF, 87 pages, 3 MB.
  - 6th meeting: Minutes of Sixth Conference, OPEC, Geneva, Switzerland, July 6-14, 1964 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_006)
    Delegations in attendancd: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics discussed included the drop in oil production in Saudi Arabia, and questions about its likely causes; a proposed embargo by OPEC members on shipments of oil to South Africa, in order to protest that state's policy of apartheid; the formation and function of an inter-OPEC court, the intention of Algeria to join OPEC as a member state, and discussions of how member states negotiate with oil companies for setting oil prices.
    PDF, 134 pages, 6 MB.
  - 7th meeting: Minutes of Seventh Conference of OPEC, Djakarta, Indonesia, November 23-28, 1964 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_007)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics discussed included modifications to OPEC's statutes, delineation of the role of Secretary General and the proposed role of Deputy Secretary General, the budget for 1965, the role of royalties paid by oil companies to OPEC member governments, and continued difficulties in negotiations for such, report of the OPEC Economic Commission (regarding pricing), the nomination of Ashraf Lutfi (Kuwait) to serve as the next Secretary General
    PDF, 158 pages, 7 MB.
  - 8th meeting: Proceedings of the Eighth Conference (Extraordinary), Geneva, 5-10 April, 1965 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_008)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Libya, Kuwait, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Discussions largely centered around the question of excess production and whether OPEC could limit excess production and stabilize or increase oil prices, including how production allocations among member countries would be determined, and what the side effects of this could be. The delegates presented and approved a production program, reviewed changes in the organization's statutes, and also discussed moving the headquarters of OPEC from Geneva to another country, with Austria being the leading candidate.
    PDF, 101 pages, 5 MB.
  - 9th meeting: Draft Minutes of the Ninth Conference, Tripoli, Libya, July 7-13, 1965 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_009)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics discussed included the findings of an appended report from the Economic Commisssion, which covered topics such as obtaining price information and the implementation of a joint production program. The move of the OPEC headquarters from Geneva to Vienna was also discussed and approved, and challenges related to obtaining pricing information from companies working in Qatar were addressed. Text of speeches by Manuel Perez Guerrero (Venezuela), Fuad al-Kabazi (Libya)
    PDF, 117 pages, 5 MB.
  - 9th meeting: Report to the Ninth Conference, OPEC Economic Commission, June 28, 1965 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_010)
    Items covered--and later discussed at the meeting in Tripoli in July 1965--included pricing information, draft letter to oil companies requesting crude oil assay data (relevant to situation in Qatar), weaknesses in Libyan oil prices attributed to activities of independent oil companies there, and methods for implementing a joint production program.
    PDF, 66 pages, 2 MB.
  - 10th meeting: Minutes of the 10th OPEC Conference, held in Vienna, Austria, December 15-17, 1965 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_011)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Discussion included question of whether individual governments should negotiate allowances with oil companies, or whether should have unified approach driven by OPEC; as well as the amendment of the Libyan Petroleum Law, the proposed budget for 1966, and how the implementation of the joint production program would be impacted by production levels of non-OPEC producers, such as Abu Dhabi and Nigeria. The role of countries that had been observers at OPEC meetings, such as Algeria, Colombia, and Trinidad, was discussed, and whether those countries should be persuaded to join as members. Ashraf Lutfi's term as Secretary General was extended by one year, and the decision to appoint a Deputy Secretary General was deferred to the next meeting.
    PDF, 110 pages, 7 MB.
  - 11th meeting: Minutes of the 11th OPEC conference, held in Vienna, Austria, April 25-28, 1966 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_012)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Observer: Algeria. Topics discussed included the proposal to use prices reported as a means of imposing income taxes on companies in the member countries, the further development of the joint production program, the invitation to Nigeria to attend the next conference as an observer, and comments from the Algerian observer in attendance.
    PDF, 142 pages, 8 MB.
  - 12th meeting: Supplemental Report to the Twelfth Conference, OPEC Economic Commission, Kuwait, November 1966 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_013)
    Topics included the submission of pricing data by oil companies to governments (citing example of Qatar), gathering data about oil exports by destination, and a review of the work of the seven previous meetings of the commission toward defining the Joint Production Programme.
    PDF, 32 pages, 1 MB
  - 12th meeting: Minutes of the 12th OPEC Conference, held in Kuwait, December 4-8, 1966 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_014)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Observer: Nigeria. Topics included adoption of 1967 budget, amendments to OPEC statute (concerning reorganization of Secretariat), proposed declaratory statement on oil policy, the proposed invitation to the emirate of Abu Dhabi to attend as an observer or to discuss possible membership, the further development of the Joint Production Programme, application of posted prices for tax purposes, production levels, review of the first meeting of national oil companies held in Caracas in October 1966, nomination of Mohammed Saleh Joukhdar of Saudi Arabia to be the next Secretary General, extending of invitations to Nigeria, Algeria, and Colombia to attend subsequent meetings as observers, with the hope that their countries would join as members, and texts of speeches by retiring president (Dr. Saleh Kubba), incoming president (Sheikh Sabah al-Ahmed al-Sabah, of Kuwait), and observer from Nigeria (F.R.A. Marinho) and closing speech by acting president Khaled al-Jasar.
    PDF, 111 pages, 5 MB.
  - 13th meeting: Minutes of the 13th (Extraordinary) Conference of OPEC, held in Rome, September 15 - 17, 1967 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_015)
    Delegations in attendance: Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics included the effect of the closure of the Suez Canal due to the Six Day War and Israeli occupation of Sinai, including the increase in oil prices passed on to consumers and the increase in freight rates charged by oil tankers, and the corresponding proposal at the meeting to levy taxes on them. In addition, the members agreed to extend an invitation to the emirate of Abu Dhabi to join OPEC.
    PDF, 19 pages, 1 MB.
  - 14th meeting: Draft minutes of the Fourteenth OPEC Conference, held in Vienna, November 27 - 29, 1967; PDF, 50 pages, 2 MB. (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_016)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics included welcoming Abu Dhabi as a new member, the discussion of the 1968 budget, the proposed elimination of allowances and gravity correction, presentation of a report on the impact of proposed taxation of tanker earnings, discussion of a report from the Economic Commission on the proposed Production Programme, proposed outreach to consumers by establishing an office in Brussels to interact with the EEC, nomination of Francisco Parra of Venezuela as the next Secretary General.
  - 15th meeting: Final Minutes of the Fifteenth (Extraordinary) OPEC Conference, held in Beirut, January 8 - 9, 1968 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_017)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics included the proposed elimination of the allowance off posted prices and gravity differential, and definitions of the proposed Uniform Petroleum Law.
    PDF, 63 pages, 3 MB.
  - 16th meeting: Minutes of the Sixteenth OPEC Conference, held in Vienna, June 24 - 25, 1968 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_018)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics included the continued development of Uniform Principles for Petroleum Legislation (in member countries), whether these should be embodied in a code or guiding principles, and whether they should be binding on all member countries, since contexts varied in each one. Discussion also ensued about the possible devaluation of the U.S. dollar and its potential impact on crude prices, the possibility of posting a senior OPEC officer to Brussels to be a liaison with the EEC,
    PDF, 92 pages, 5 MB.
  - 17th meeting: Minutes of the Seventeenth OPEC Conference, held in Baghdad, November 9-10, 1968 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_019)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics included the proposal of a conservation regulation, the summary of the Economic Commission report concerning the implementation of a Joint Production Program, the relationship between OPEC and national oil companies, participation of governments of member states in concession-holding companies, the 1969 budget, and the nomination of Hassan Kamel of Qatar to be the next Secretary General. Also included texts of speeches by President Ahmed Hassan al-Bakr of Iraq, OPEC President Abdul Rahman al Ateeqy of Kuwait, and Secretary General Francisco Parra of Venezuela.
    PDF, 65 pages, 3 MB.
  - 18th meeting: Minutes of the Eighteenth OPEC Conference, held in Vienna, July 8 - 9, 1969 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_020)
    Delegations in attenadnce: Abu Dhabi, Algeria, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics include welcoming Algeria to full membership in OPEC,the impact of the proposed devaluation of the U.S. dollar on oil prices, policies regarding the posting of oil prices, the role of national oil companies in relation to OPEC, contacts with the EEC, and the role of English as the language used in OPEC meetings (which Algeria disputed).
    Also includes text of opening speech by Rashid al-Rifai, of Iraq, president of OPEC, and Sid al-Ghozali, head of the Algerian delegation.
    PDF, 78 pages, 5 MB.
  - 19th meeting: Minutes of the Nineteenth OPEC Conference, held in Doha, December 14 - 16, 1969 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_021)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Algeria, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics included pricing, the production program, relinquishment, an Algerian plan to revise fiscal regime of agreements (with French oil companies operating in Algeria), the role of meetings of national oil companies in contrast to general OPEC meetings, and the proposed construction of permanent headquarters for OPEC in Vienna.
    Also included text of speeches by Sheikh Ahmed bin Ali Al-Thani, ruler of Qatar; Nadim Pachachi, of Abu Dhabi, president of the 18th conference of OPEC; and Elrich Sanger, Secretary General.
    PDF, 65 pages, 4 MB.
- Minutes of OPEC meetings, 1970-1975; 122.0 Megabytes in 33 PDF documents.
  - 20th meeting: Minutes of the Twentieth OPEC Conference, held in Algiers, June 24 - 26, 1970 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_022)
    Delegations in attendance: Topics included the report of the Economic Commission, which included the continuing discussion about the formation of a production program, a discussion of the role of national oil companies in relation to OPEC, discussion of a report on participation, and the presentation of findings of a special committee tasked with analyzing the structure of OPEC. Focus toward the end of the meeting was given on issues in Iraq regarding oil companies' production policies and royatly expensing there. Texts of speeches included those of opening addresses by Hassan Kamel of Qatar, the president for the 19th conference, and Algerian President Houari Boumediene.
    PDF, 133 pages, 8 MB.
  - 20th meeting: Report of the Economic Commission 14th and 15th meetings (Vienna, Algiers), June 1970 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_023)
    The report, included as item 6 of the agenda for the 20th conference held in Algiers, was a summary of two meetings of the Economic Commission, held in Vienna in April 1970 and in Algiers, concurrent with the 20th conference, in June 1970. An analysis of consumer use in various countries was presented to inform the proposals for a joint production program for OPEC member nations.
    PDF, 9 pages, 211 KB.
  - 21st meeting: Minutes of the Twenty-First OPEC Conference, held in Caracas, December 9 - 12, 1970 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_024)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Algeria, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. The conference was divided up into five meetings, and the minutes divided accordingly. The first meeting include the election of a president for the conference, approval of the agenda and minutes, and the like, before a discussion of disparities in member states in posted crude oil prices. The second meeting consisted of a report from the Economic Commission, the third meeting was a discussion about the draft proposal for a Production Program. The fourth meeting covered issues related to participation, the national oil companies, the 1971 budget, and other administrative issues. The fifth meeting included draft resolutions from Algeria and Libya, and a closed meeting of delegation heads selected Nadim Pachachi of Abu Dhabi as the next Secretary General. The minutes include the text of opening speeches by Belaid Abdesselam of Algeria, in his role as conference president for this meeting, and Rafael Caldera, president of Venezuela.
    PDF, 127 pages, 8 MB.
  - 22nd meeting: Minutes of the Twenty-Second OPEC Conference (Extraordinary), held in Tehran, February 3 - 4, 1971 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_025)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Algeria, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. Topics discussed largely focused on Resolution 120, as adopted at the previous conference, which addressed rates of taxation on oil companies relative to established prices on crude oil. Countries which had implemented this reported on their experiences, those that had not yet been successful in doing so looked at strategies for doing that. At a special session held in the Iranian Senate, the conference was addressed by Shah Mohamed Reza Pahlavi, who addressed the urgency of implementing this resolution to address price imbalances among oil-producing countries, and to rectify the drop in oil prices among some producing countries, such as the nations of the Gulf region, including Iran. Text of opening speech by Hugo Perez de Salvia of Venezuela, the president of the 21st conference, Jamshid Amouzegar, head of the Iranian delegation, and Shah Mohamed Reza Pahlavi of Iran, is included.
    PDF, 61 pages, 4 MB.
  - 23rd meeting: Minutes of the Twenty-Third OPEC Conference (Extraordinary), held in Vienna, July 10, 1971 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_026)
    Delegations in attendance: Abu Dhabi, Algeria, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Venezuela. The meeting consisted chiefly of discussion of the findings of a standing committee on the proposed Joint Production Program, which having seen such a program as too complex, proposed a simpler means of reducing oil production among all members when market prices dropped beneath an acceptable level for a sustained period of time. A resolution to this effect was concluded.
    PDF, 14 pages, 872 KB.
  - 24th meeting: Minutes of the Twenty-Fourth Meeting of the OPEC Conference, held in Vienna, July 12 - 13, 1971 (Box E-records AD_MC_038, Object E-records AD_MC_038_027)